Today's דף, daf, we're דף daf behind, it's י"ז, Yud Zayin, and
we've been a little more behind, we pick up on ט"ז עמוד
ב' Tes Zayin amud bais at the two dots, but we're going
to catch up today to be one דף daf behind and then
catch up on Shabbos. Okay, אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, about a third
of the way, about fifteen lines down to the two dots. Okay.
So,
המוציא שטר הקנאה בשוק, Hamotzi shtar hakna'ah bashuk, so we had a
whole discussion right about questions around about if you buy and feel
that you know as you know that the guy doesn't own or
finds out that he doesn't own it, to what degree is it
insured and he can get reimbursed for the principle and for the
שבח, shevach, and all of those discussions. Okay. Now we get back
to finding and returning שטרות. shtarot. And we're going to revisit all
the issues, or many of the issues we discussed before, about are
we concerned for פירעון, pira'on, are we concerned for קנוניא, kenunya, a
scheme, all those types of issues. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel,
המוציא שטר הקנאה בשוק, Hamotzi shtar hakna'ah bashuk, if somebody finds in
the marketplace a שטר הקנאה shtar hakna'ah which is a שטר shtar
which as you might remember, there a קנין kinyan was done to
make the liens active even before the money was lent. So therefore,
because it's a שטר הקנאה, shtar hakna'ah, there's no concern that the
שטר shtar was written and then it wasn't used, and from the
very moment it was written, those liens became active. Right? A normal
שטר shtar says Michael borrowed a thousand dollars from me.
Michael holds on to it until he borrows the thousand dollars. But
if we made it as a שטר הקנאה, shtar hakna'ah, then even
before he borrowed the thousand dollars, I have a lien and I
have a right of a thousand dollars on Michael's property. So even
if he never borrowed the money, from that moment I had those
rights. So then the only question is,
Michael has possession, well Michael starts with possession of it, but the
point is, I mean, as soon as it's written, I have those
rights and he has to hand it over to me.
Now,
so in that case where there's no concern, it immediately became active,
think about it like, you know, activating your credit card, immediately became
active, but the question still is, I might in the end, right,
Michael might have paid me the thousand dollars and then I would
give it back to him and he would tear it up. So
the concern is a concern not about כתב ללוות ולא ללוה, kosav
lilvos velo lova, that's not a concern by שטרי הקנאה, shtarei hakna'ah,
but there is a potential concern of פירעון, pira'on, that after Michael
actually paid me, maybe it's then, then he gets the שטר shtar
back and he gets to tear it up.
We'll discuss later the date, okay, but for now we're assuming it
doesn't. So in that case יחזרו לבעלים, yachziru lib'alim, give it back
to me. דאי משום דכתב ללוות ולא ללוה, de'i mishum dechosav lilvos
velo lova, if it's because of a concern, yeah, in this case
you owe me money, I know in the last דף daf I
owed you money now you owe me money, I'm the בעלים, ba'alim,
I'm the one who for whom the שטר shtar was written to
be given to. דאי משום דכתב ללוות ולא ללוה, de'i mishum dechosav
lilvos velo lova, if there was a concern that Michael was going
to borrow money but he never wound up borrowing it, השבינהו, hashiveihu,
that's why it's a שטר הקנאה, shtar hakna'ah, so it doesn't matter
if he ever borrowed the money, he owes me the money from
the day it was the קנין kinyan was done and the שטר
shtar was written. ואי משום פירעון, ve'i mishum pira'on, wait a minute,
but maybe Michael paid me up and I gave him back the
שטר shtar and he dropped it, לא חיישינן לפירעון, lo chaishinan lipira'on,
we're not concerned about that, דאם איתא דפרעיה, de'im isa dipar'ei, if
Michael had paid it up, מקרע הוה קרע ליה, mikra hava kara
leh, he would have torn it up right away. So you might
remember a few days ago, a דף daf or so ago, we
referred to שמואל Shmuel who's לא חייש לפירעון, lo chaish lipira'on, this
is the שמואל Shmuel that we referred to like three days ago.
Okay, you see it says on the side, י"ד עמוד א'. Yud
Daled amud aleph. Alright. לא חיישינן לפירעון. lo chaishinan lipira'on. Okay, it's
the assumption that it would automatically be torn up. אמר רב נחמן,
Amar Rav Nachman,
אבא מן ספרי דייני דמר שמואל הוה, Abba min safrei dayanei deMar
Shmuel hava, my father was one of the סופרים, soferim, was one
of the scribes of שמואל, Shmuel, והוינא כבר שית כבר שבע, vehavina
kevar sheis kevar sheva, and I was like six or seven years
old, ודכירנא, vedachirna, and I remember, דהוו מכרזי ואמרי, dehavu machrizei ve'amrei,
that he would announce and say, הני שטרי אקנייתא דמשתכחי בשוקא, hanei
shtarei aknyeisa demishtakchei bishuka,
those שטרי קנין, shtarei kinyan, you know, שטרות shtarot that have that
obligation from the moment they were written, that are found in the
marketplace in the street, נהדרינהו למריהו, nahadrinhu lemareihu, return them to their
owners, return them to the person who for whom they were written,
the מלווה. malveh.
Okay, and how often does that happen?
I know a little recollection you mean, or you may happen that
people find these שטרות? shtarot? Yeah, I don't know.
I have a different question. Yes. Where do you think that announcement
was made? My thought is on Shabbos in shul.
Oh it could be.
So interesting, but they used to do like call for צדקה tzedakah
in shul. Right, right.
Could be, you're right, it could be. Okay, okay, could be, yeah,
where was, yeah, maybe it was made in shul on Shabbos, I
don't know. אמר רב עמרם, Amar Rav Amram, אנן תנינא, anan tanina,
we also taught, and this is a משנה mishnah coming up, כל
מעשה בית דין הרי זה יחזיר, kol ma'aseh beis din harei zeh
yachzir, any document that is issued from the court should be returned.
Now presumably it means the court issued it in favor of a
particular person. Okay, so what type of a document are we talking
about? אלמא לא חיישינן לפירעון, alma lo chaishinan lipira'on, so presumably that's
a case where you don't have to be concerned of כתב ללוות
ולא ללוה, kosav lilvos velo lova, obviously it's not relevant, right, you
know Michael and David here come to a court case, and the
court will write a document and says Michael is, you know, Michael
has won this judgment, David owes him a thousand dollars, and we
have that document and we give it to Michael, so there's no
כתב ללוות ולא ללוה, kosav lilvos velo lova, from the moment we
wrote it, right, it was a valid like was an active document
and, you know, and David had to pay, so the only concern
is that David... paid Michael the money and then the document didn't
get written up. Okay, so obviously it shows אלמא לא חיישינן לפרעון
alma lo chayshenan l'peron we're not concerned that it was paid up,
because if it was paid up it would have been torn up.
Is that the person who said כתב ללוה ולא
לוה?
kasav l'loveh
v'lo lava?
כתב ללוה ולא לוה. kasav l'loveh v'lo lava. It was written for
money to be borrowed which was never borrowed, yes.
Sir, another question. I know גיטין Gittin we're going crazy about maybe
there's two יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben Shimon in the same city,
right? Right. Here like that's totally not a concern about...
yeah, I don't know,
that might have been a special לשמה, lishmah, we just took it
that far?
That might have been a special גיטין Gittin issue, but it might
be worth to have a conversation where we write the שטר shtar
to the way we need it to be specific, you know?
No, no, but if I find it in the שוק, shuk, how
do I know it's me?
There could be another Michael. Oh, so that's a yeah, yeah, so
that's a good question. That's a good question. So you're right, we
have... that has to be dealt with. But we're not getting there
right now, okay? I have to check, I have to... I don't
remember if that comes up here. It certainly is the case by
גיטין. Gittin. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay,
so you see it's implicit in the משנה Mishnah what you see
the משנה Mishnah is not concerned for פרעון. peron. So the גמרא
Gemara says אמר ליה רב זירא amlei Rav Zeira מתניתין בשטרי חלטתא
ואדרכתא matnisin b'shtarei chaltasa v'adrachta דלאו בני פרעון נינהו. d'lav b'nei peron
ninhu. No, our משנה Mishnah maybe it is a type of a
שטר shtar that you can't... obviously there's not an issue of פרעון.
peron. Why? Because let's say what the בית דין Beis Din issued
for to Michael was David owed Michael a thousand dollars and we've
assessed that, you know, that Michael's nice Nikon camera (see I'm switching
from iPhones) nice Nikon camera's worth a thousand dollars and Michael has
a right to take that Nikon camera in payment of his debt.
Okay, actually we would more be talking about a plot of land.
He's got this nice little plot of land, okay, and in that
case, what do you mean פרעון? peron? Either Michael has the camera
or doesn't have the camera. Either he's on the plot of land
or he's not on the plot of land. So in that type
of a case, right, there's not a question of whether or not
it's been paid up. Okay, we can go and see does Michael
have that plot of land that he was awarded? Does he have
that camera that he was awarded? We can see whether it's been
paid. Okay, but in a case where we can't see, maybe we
are concerned for פרעון. peron. All right.
How do you translate the word חלטתא? chaltasa?
So חלטתא chaltasa is basically that a...
yeah, basically right, we awarded a piece of property to you. Like
רש"י Rashi says, we assessed a property in payment of your debt.
And now there's also the word אדרכתא adrachta because אדרכתא adrachta basically
gives you a right to discover property and seize it. But then
תוספות Tosafos says, so then how do you know whether... what do
you mean לא חיישינן לפרעון? lo chayshenan l'peron? Like how do you
know what that property was and whether it was or wasn't seized?
So תוספות Tosafos sort of, you know, glosses over the word אדרכתא
adrachta or says it's not in some גירסא. girsas. I don't know.
Okay. אמר רבא amar Rava והני לאו בני פרעון נינהו? v'hani lav
b'nei peron ninhu? What do you mean that those can't be paid
up? והאמר נהרדעי v'ha'amar Nehardei שומא הדר תרי עשר ירחי שתא. shuma
hadar atrei asar yarchai shata.
That you have twelve months, even after something has been assessed, to
buy back the property. Okay, so Michael goes ahead and he seizes
this acre of land that we have specified that he can take
from David. And now David actually has a year to pay back
Michael the thousand dollars and retake that piece of land. Does that
mean he has forever? Doesn't he? No. What we're going to see,
that's the next opinion. Okay, so we might as well read it
since you said it. Okay. שומא הדר תרי עשר ירחי שתא. shuma
hadar atrei asar yarchai shata. ואמר אמימר v'amar Amemar אנא מנהרדעא אנא
וסבירא לי דשומא הדר
לעולם. ana mi'Nehardea ana v'savira li d'shuma hadar l'olam. That you can
always buy it back. Now that's not true, that you get forever.
You know, the logic is: he owed me a thousand dollars, this
is the money I took for payment of it, end of the
deal, my debt's been paid off. Why does he have a right
to buy back this property? Okay, let' say he handed you the
plot of land. Would he have a right to buy it back?
So we're going to talk in a minute why he has that
right. But given that he has that right, it says: what do
you mean that you don't know whether it's been paid up or
not? David could be sitting on the plot of land, Michael says
it hasn't been paid up, and David says it has been paid
up because he took the land and then I paid him back
for it. And therefore that שטר shtar goes to me because the
debt has been paid. So you cannot look at the property and
determine whether or not the debt has been paid because even though
we awarded the property to Michael, David had a right to buy
it back. So you see if we're still willing to give this
שטר shtar to Michael and assume it hasn't been paid, that means
we're not concerned for פרעון. peron. Okay.
And now we look at the case like later, let's say I
took the land, which every right I had to do based on
this, and according to this נהרדעי Nehardei second opinion or אמימר, Amemar,
you know, says he has a right to buy back. I already
put in שבח. shevach.
All right, we're not going to go there. Okay, but I mean
that's a relevant discussion, we're not going to go there. Anyway the
גמרא Gemara says like this: so anyway, the point is that since
even that case is given for פרעון peron and we're not concerned,
it proves like שמואל Shmuel that לא חיישינן לפרעון. lo chayshenan l'peron.
So... so
the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רבא ella amar Rava התם היינו
טעמא דאמרי אי דאפסידה נפשיה. hasam hainu ta'ama d'amri ee d'afsidah nafshei.
No, no, no. There, there, you're right, there we're not concerned for
פרעון, peron, but the reason is the following: it's a reason that
is specific to the case of the שומא, shuma, the case of
the שטרי חלטתא. shtar chaltasa. So you're right, we're not concerned for
פרעון peron but in that case. But nevertheless and even though it's
possible that David bought it back and the whole thing
But the reason we're not concerned is a specific reason that's not
relevant to a normal שטר חוב. shtar chov. Why? What's the reason
there it's not a concern? דאמרינן da-amrinan because we say אי הוא
דאפסיד אנפשיה. ee hu de-afsid anafshei. You know David, if you actually
brought back that plot from Michael and you were not careful with
the שטר shtar whatever, you were being completely irresponsible. Why? דבעידנא דפרע
איבעי ליה למיקרעיה לשטרא. de-be-idna de-para ibai lay le-mikrayeh le-shatara. Because at
the time when you paid it up, now we could say this
so far we could say this by any שטר חוב, shtar chov,
but we'll see why this is unique or just distinct. At the
time when you paid it up you should have either torn up
that שטר shtar that allowed him to seize the property, אי נמי
למכתב שטרא אחרינא עלויה, ee nami le-michtav shatara achrina ilvay, or to
get him to write a שטר shtar for you, not a receipt,
because here he's basically giving you back the land, so you should
have got a sale document from him that he was essentially giving
you back the land for the money you gave him. Now why
should you have been more careful there than in a normal חוב?
chov? Because now we're going to explain why שומא הדר. shuma hadar.
דמדינא ארעא לא בעי למיהדר de-midina ara lo bay le-mihadar because really
land shouldn't have to go back. That land was taken in payment
of a debt, end of story, it's Michael's. Why should you have
a right to buy it back? Okay,
ומשום ועשית הישר והטוב בעיני השם, u-mishum ve-asisa ha-yashar ve-ha-tov be-einai Hashem,
because of doing the right thing הוא דאמר רבנן תהדר. hu de-amru
rabbanan tehadar. The Rabbis said, you know Michael, in the end of
the day it was about the thousand dollars, it wasn't about the
plot of land. This is David's plot of land, you should do
the right thing if he's willing to give you the money, give
him back the land. Now Michael asks a good question, let's say
I've already invested money, let's say a million other things. Okay, we
don't know, we're not going into that right now. What's actually quite
fascinating though is
the guy sitting
in the front, well okay, that's an interesting question. What if those
things have happened? But let's not go in there right now. Hold
on, let me just finish my sentence. Okay, what is interesting is
that we have
institutionalized ועשית הישר והטוב, ve-asisa ha-yashar ve-ha-tov, which I find fascinating because
ועשית הישר והטוב ve-asisa ha-yashar ve-ha-tov is normally about doing the spirit
of the law and here we have sort of institutionalized it. And
the interesting question is to what degree have we institutionalized it? אמרו
רבנן תהדר. amru rabbanan tehadar. If Michael says I refuse, is he
entitled to refuse? What limits are there, as Michael says cases that
look like ריבית, ribbis, cases that Michael invested money? But anyway, it's
a fascinating, we're not going into it because we don't have time
because anyway it's not here in the גמרא, Gemara, but it is
a fascinating look into an institutionalization of ועשית הישר והטוב. ve-asisa ha-yashar
ve-ha-tov. Anyway, well whatever, there's a couple סוגיות sugyos in יבמות, Yevamos,
whatever, I can give you some articles. Anyway, but הוא דאמרו רבנן
תהדר. hu de-amru rabbanan tehadar. Therefore הלכך, hilchach, because legally David really
isn't entitled to it, so he has to appreciate that when Michael
gives him back that land, it really is Michael's land that he's
giving him. He's not getting back his own land and paying up
the debt. The debt's been paid. He's really getting Michael's land. And
since he's getting in that transaction Michael's land, מעיקרא הוא דקזבין, me-ikra
hu de-kazvin, he's basically doing a new purchase now, giving Michael a
thousand dollars and buying Michael's land. And if that's fundamentally what's going
on here, איבעי ליה למכתב שטר זביני. ibai lay le-michtav shtar zvini.
Therefore, you have to know if I'm buying this plot of land,
I'm going to have to prove it's
mine, I need documentation. Okay, because there fundamentally it's a new thing
going here and if you're not getting documentation or tearing up the
evidence that Michael has, you're being irresponsible. So in this case we're
not concerned for פירעון. piraon. Okay, in this case it's your fault,
your responsibility and we give it back to Michael. But גבי שטר
חוב, gabai shtar chov, but by a document of debt, now even
though there you should say just be responsible and tear it up,
but מצי למימר, matzi le-meimar, what would you say there? You'd say
the same
thing, אי חזא דפרע איבעי ליה למיקרעיה לשטרא, ee chaza de-para ibai
lay le-mikrayeh le-shatara, then he should have got the document and torn
it up. אמר אשתמוטי קא משתמיט ליה, amar ishtamutei ka mishtamit lay,
maybe the
מלווה malveh is basically trying to get out of it and saying
אמר ליה למחר אהבינא לך, amar lay le-machar avina lach, you know
what, I'll give you, I don't have the שטר shtar on me
today, I'll give it back to you tomorrow. Thank you for the
thousand dollars you owe me, I'll get you the שטר shtar tomorrow
when I get it. השתא ליתא גבאי, hashta leisa gaba'ee, I don't
happen to have it. Now maybe you could say if you're smart
you would say fine I'll wait to pay you the money, but
the מלווה malveh saying
you're a year overdue with paying me the money, you got to
pay me, that's not an excuse, I'll give you the שטר shtar
tomorrow. So obviously you're in a disadvantaged position there and you have
a responsibility to pay back the money, so therefore maybe you paid
it up without immediately getting the שטר. shtar. In a plot of
land
you wouldn't have done that?
Right, because there you don't owe the money whatever, you are the
one initiating a new transaction in that case. אי נמי אפישיטיה דספרא
זייר ליה, ee nami apishitei de-safra zayer lay, or maybe the הלכה
halacha is that when you pay the שטר, shtar, when you finally
pay up the debt, you the לוה, loveh, you actually also have
to pay for the costs of drawing up the document. Okay, it's
your responsibility as the לוה loveh to pay the סופר sofer cost.
So you haven't paid that yet, so I'm going to tell you,
you know what, I'm going to give you back your שטר shtar
when you reimburse me for the costs of drawing up the
document, okay? The initial document. So therefore, because in that case the
dynamic is different, if we were to use modern terms we would
say sort of the power dynamic is different in that
case, okay, it's quite possible that you did not get the שטר
shtar to tear up. But in the other case where it's not
your land and you are coming to buy land that really isn't
yours and you're like the initiator and you don't have to be
doing this whole thing, if you are doing it you're... You have
to be taking- you have to obviously be doing the responsible thing
and ensure that you're going to get a שטר shtar to go
with it. So the bottom line is, the משנה mishnah says that
you return these court documents. It seems to be a proof for
not concerned for פירעון, piraon, and the גמרא's Gemara answer is it
might be a- that- it might be- and the גמרא's Gemara answer
is it might be a special case. A special case of seizing
land that even though פירעון piraon might be possible there, there's special
reasons why there's not a concern of פירעון piraon in those cases,
okay, because- because either פירעון piraon doesn't exist or because it should
definitely come with a tearing up of the שטר. shtar. And maybe
in a normal שטר חוב shtar chov maybe where the likelihood is
greater, maybe we are still concerned with פירעון. piraon. So it's not
a proof for שמואל. Shmuel. Yes, Dov.
Now before you said that it was like a new sale from
the גמרא, Gemara, it sounds like seizing the land but holding it
as-
No, but that's exactly not the point. That's why מן הדין min
hadin you don't have the right to buy it back. It's ועשית
הישר והטוב. veasita hayashar vehatov. You're not seizing and holding it. You
are taking it in payment of the debt.
So it's not collateral until- Correct.
That's exactly why it's considered a new sale.
Any concern about payment
in the scenario that the- the- the לוה loveh
paid back the מלווה malveh before the seizure?
Correct. Rather, aren't we concerned that that happened and the שטר shtar
fell from the לוה. loveh. Okay. We have to have fewer questions
now because we are definitely- I'm committed to catching up, or catching
up to be a day behind. אמר רב עמרם אמר רבי יוחנן.
Amar Rav Amram amar Rabbi Yochanan. המוצא שטר חוב בשוק, Hamotzi shtar
chov bashuk, אף על פי שכתוב בו הנפק. af al pi shekatuv
bo hanpek. Now you have a document, a loan document, which is
not a שטר הקנאה, shtar hakna'ah, so it might not have ever
been used. But it's been validated by the בית דין, Beis Din,
the signatures, and validation only happens when the מלווה malveh presents it.
So again it's a type of a case that you would definitely
know that the money has been- has been lent. So therefore the
only concern is פירעון. piraon. So in that case, לא יחזיר לבעלים.
lo yachazir labaalim. Do not return to the owners. A different ruling
than שמואל. Shmuel. לא מיבעיא היכא דלא כתב בו הנפק, Lo mibaya
heicha delo kasav bo hanpek, it goes without saying if there's been
no validation, דאיכא למימר כתב ללוות ולא לוה, de'ika lemeimar kasav lilvos
velo lova, maybe it was used to borrow and no money was
ever borrowed. ואפילו כתב בו הנפק, Va'afilu kasav bo hanpek, even if
בית דין Beis Din has validated
the signatures, ומאי ניהו דמקוים, umai nihu demikuyam, it's interesting you have
to now explain what that means. It's the signatures have been validated.
לא יחזיר. Lo yachazir. So even though we know the מלווה malveh
had it and the money was lent, don't give it back to
the מלווה, malveh, דחיישינן לפירעון. dechaishinan lepiraon. Again, against שמואל, Shmuel, we
are concerned about being paid up. Now we're going to do the
same thing with the משנה mishnah we have- with the משנה mishnah
about מעשה בית דין. maaseh Beis Din. איתיביה רבי ירמיה לרבי אבהו:
Eisivei Rabbi Yirmiyah le-Rabbi Abbahu: כל מעשה בית דין הרי זה יחזיר.
Kol maaseh Beis Din harei zeh yachazir. Look, you return מעשה בית
דין, maaseh Beis Din, you see we're not concerned for
פירעון. piraon. אמר ליה רבי ירמיה ברי- Amar leh Rabbi Yirmiyah beri
is it
ברי? beri?
ברי, Beri, yeah. אמר ליה רבי ירמיה ברי.
Amar
leh Rabbi Yirmiyah beri. אה ירמיה ברי.
Oh
Yirmiyah beri. Oh, I see, thank you. Okay. All right, because it's
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah says to רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. Oh, thank
you. Okay. So אמר ליה ירמיה ברי, amar leh Yirmiyah beri, ירמיה
Yirmiyah my son. לאו כל מעשה בית דין שווין. Lav kol maaseh
Beis Din shavin. Not all מעשה בית דין maaseh Beis Din are
the same. אלא, Ella, now you would say לא כל מעשה בית
דין שווין, lo kol maaseh Beis Din shavin, we would say like
we said before, this special case about חלטתא. chaltata. We'll get to
that in a minute. But before, he says a different
answer. אלא כגון שהוחזק כפרן. Ella kegon shehuchzak kafran. Now that's really
not distinguishing between מעשה בית דין, maaseh Beis Din, that's distinguishing between
the person, right? When are we not
concerned? Basically, I say give me back that שטר, shtar, Michael borrowed
the money from me, and Michael said yes but I paid it
up. And he's saying- so normally he'd say we be חיישינן לפירעון.
chaishinan lepiraon. That was the teaching by רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. But
here, why do we give it back to me? Why do we
give it back in מעשה בית דין? maaseh Beis Din? Because here
we don't believe Michael. Why don't we believe Michael here? Because it's
a case where Michael is known to have at the past claimed
he paid something off and he didn't pay it off. So now
he's not believed- what? So why do they let him borrow? I
don't know, but anyway, you know, maybe it was an old debt.
So now that's why he's not believed. Normally the answer would be
you're wrong, לא חיישינן לפירעון- lo chaishinan lepiraon wait, wait, wait, wait.
Yeah, right. No, right. Normally you're right, meaning רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu
says normally חיישינן לפירעון. chaishinan lepiraon. The reason in the משנה mishnah
we give it back is because you can't trust the other guy.
It's a special case that you can't trust the other guy, which
is not about different מעשה בית דין, maaseh Beis Din, it's about
different guys. You can't trust the other guy. אלא כגון שהוחזק כפרן.
Ella kegon shehuchzak kafran. That's the only reason that you- that you
give it back in the משנה. mishnah. אמר רבא משום דהוחזק כפרן
חדא זימנא תו לא פרע כלל? Amar Rava mishum dehuchzak kafran chada
zimna tu lo para klal? So there's a very nice sort of
idea. Okay. Just because Michael in the past has denied debt, does
that mean that he'll never pay up a debt?
I mean, חזקה chazakah with one time?
Well, okay, but you know, yeah, I don't know. But normally we
say הוחזק כפרן huchzak kafran not in the three-time חזקה chazakah meaning
it's been proven that you've lied. Okay, now that's a very interesting
case, right? Because we do have cases before if you remember about
a guy that lied and you know, and he's פסול לעדות, pasul
le'eidus, etc.
Okay, but you know, there's two questions I guess. There's one question
in a person's capacity as an עד. ed. If a person is
a proven liar, whatever, can he testify for other people? There's another
principle when he's just defending his own interests. All of a sudden
means everybody can take like advantage of him because any claim he
makes as a litigant is going to be completely thrown out of
court because once he was known to have lied. That's one issue.
The other issue also though is that if you might remember before,
there was different types of things. I might lie on a debt.
But not be פסול לעדות pasul l'eidus because אשתמוטי קא משתמיט, ishtamutei
kamishtameit, I'm trying to sort of avoid and get out of it,
I'm not really trying to steal it and so on.
Not מודה במקצת? moda b'miktzat?
No, well
that's just in general, you know, if somebody is כופר kofer whatever
and and we say he's trying to sort of avoid like he's
not really trying to steal just avoid for the time being, he's
not really פסול לעדות. pasul l'eidus. So that might be going on
here as well. But this point just seems to be even beyond
that, that you cannot now say that this person as a litigant
all of his claims are completely disqualified. Right, I don't know, you
know, let's say you got a guy that was, you know, a
murderer, and now he's but now he's dealing in a civil suit
with somebody. You say oh this guy's a murderer everything he says
is a lie so we you know of course we're just going
to award everything to the guy who's standing against him. As a
civil as as a litigant you don't you know you you still
have normal dealings and you might be telling the truth in this
case. So and anyway the fact that you might be lying, any
litigant might be lying because of their own best interests. All right,
so the גמרא's Gemara it's a fascinating point that just because you're
הוחזק כפרן huchzak kafran in other cases does not mean that your
claim here is complete is rejected. So, בסולה פרקלאו, bisula parklav, אלא
אמר רבא מתניתין בשטר חלטתא ואדרכתא וכדרבי זירא ella amar Rava masnisin
b'shtar chaltaza v'adrachta uch'Rabbi Zeira like we said before. Okay, our משנה
Mishna would be a case of a certain type that's a really
local מעשה בית דין שווי, maiseh beis din shavi, a certain type
of a שטר בית דין shtar beis din that we're not concerned
for פירעון, piraon, a writ of seizure. That case we're not concerned
for פירעון, piraon, but you know רבי אבא Rabbi Abba in the
name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is still entitled to say as
a general rule you don't give back a שטר חוב shtar chov
because חיישינן לפירעון. chaishinan l'piraon. Okay, so there's the general debate of
שמואל Shmuel and רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. שמואל Shmuel says לא חיישינן
לפירעון lo chaishinan l'piraon if you know the money was lent or
you know the obligation existed initially. And רבי אבא Rabbi Abba in
the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said even if you know
the money was lent or the money existed, the obligation existed, שטר
הקנאה shtar hakneh or שטר מקוים, shtar mekuyam, nevertheless חיישינן לפירעון. chaishinan
l'piraon. The משנה Mishna later that says you don't give back you
do give back מעשה בית דין, maiseh beis din, that could be
special שטרות shtarlot that don't have that concern.
So the murderer has nothing to do with anything.
Well, it's not relevant here but now we're going to spend the
rest of the דף, daf, what is today's דף daf dealing with
כפרן. kafran. So let's take a look. וכפרן הולך לו אידך בשם
רב עמרם מיורסא. v'kafran hozel lidach b'shem Rav Amram Mi'ursa.
Since we were talking about the idea of הוחזק כפרן, huchzak kafran,
let's talk
about it. דאמר רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן אמרו לו
צא תן לו דאמר פרעתי d'amar Rav Yosef bar Minyumi amar Rav
Nachman amru lo tzei ten lo d'amar parati now this is going
to be fascinating. This הלכה, halacha, they say, okay so בית דין
beis din issues a order against David in his case with Michael
and they say David, go out and pay Michael the money he
owes. And then he comes back and he says, I paid it.
נאמן. ne'eman. So he's believed.
But he hasn't swore to it, does he? Just says.
Well רש"י Rashi says נאמן, ne'eman, if you look at רש"י, Rashi,
נאמן ובשבועת היסת. ne'eman ubishvuas heses. Okay he does have to make
a שבועה, shvua, some type of a שבועה. shvua. Now this is
bizarre, right? Because they could have been arguing about this whole type
of thing or whatever and after all these proofs Michael proves that
David owes him the money and בית דין beis din after a
whole long case says David you owe him the money and then
David is believed to walk out of the בית דין beis din
and say ten minutes later I paid him up. Okay, yeah, because
it's like it's like a מלווה. milve. Now the question is that
the ראשונים Rishonim ask, wait, why is he believed? If you remember
before we said I mean the רי"ף Rif asks this, that a
ruling of בית דין beis din is like a מלווה בשטר, milve
bishtar, it gives Michael liens. Okay? So the answer is yes it's
like a מלווה בשטר milve bishtar that it's public enough and Michael
has liens, but it's not like a מלווה בשטר milve bishtar that
it prevents David from being believed to say he paid up. In
the same way if you borrow money without a שטר, shtar, you're
believed to say you paid up, you know, then here too David
is believed סתם stam to say he paid up, which is like
seems like a terrible possible abuse. Yeah, but whatever I don't know
if you did or not, but whatever. I mean I guess if
they're validating a previous שטר shtar it's different. But let's not let's
not assume that case. All we have is the ruling of the
בית דין. beis din. Okay? So it seems like that's given to
terrible abuse, everybody will just say I paid up what בית דין
beis din owes me. Okay, now, according רש"י Rashi adds the fact
that he has to swear. But anyway since there's no document, no
writ, then David is seen as all oral and therefore David is
believed to say פרעתי, parati, which just to me boggles the mind.
Okay, now, because of that, because David is just believed to say
פרעתי, parati, בעא מיניה לכתוב אין כותבין ונותנין לו. ba minei l'lichtov
ein kosvin v'nosnin lo. Now if Michael says write me a writ
that David, you know, owes me the money, then you don't write
it for him. Now why not? So the ראשונים Rishonim say that
the point is that Michael comes back a day later and says
write me a writ that David owes me the money. So we
don't write it, you know why we don't write it? Because maybe
David paid you in the last twenty-four hours. Okay, I mean they
don't say literally a day later, but whatever in the last right
let me finish my point. What?
This is the case if he said פרעתי parati then we don't
write a writ or is separate? No, David hasn't said anything. We
said David to go pay you. You come back a day later
and say look, since David is believed to say פרעתי, parati, I'd
like to have a writ that says that he owes me the
money so that he won't be believed to say פרעתי parati as
long as I'm holding onto the writ. And the answer is we
don't write it for you. Why not? Because maybe he paid you
off in the last twenty-four hours. And now he has paid you-
Then David is believed and because of that Michael doesn't can't get
a writ later. Presumably he can get a writ immediately but not
later. Okay, but if we just say חייב, chayav, that doesn't create
enough of a pressure and therefore you're not believed and therefore Michael
can get a writ. Why wouldn't it be the case where David
would say, if I'm paying you, but even if the שטר shtar
is נבלה neveilah like the previous case we had on the previous
דף, daf, give me something. Sure, if he's smart, even write me
a note I paid you. Yeah, he can say that, but that's
not an interesting case. Then he'll have documentation. The question is when
he doesn't have documentation. ורזביד משמיה דרב נחמן אמר, VeRazvid mishmei deRav
Nachman amar, בין צא תן לו בין חייב אתה ליתן לו, bein
tzei ten lo bein chayav ata liten lo, no, those distinctions don't
matter. Whether it's go pay him or whether you're obligated, ואמר פרעתי
נאמן, ve'amar parati ne'eman, either one is treated like the court is
ordering him. It's very interesting, the Rosh says that we פוסקין posken
like this second language. And you know why the Rosh says we
פוסקין posken like the second language? Because he says people nowadays don't
distinguish between צא תן לו tzei ten lo and חייב אתה ליתן
לו. chayav ata liten lo. It all sounds, people treat it all
the same. So it's interesting, like he's פוסקין poskening that position because
that's the reality in his time about how people treat those,
you know, those orders, that they treat them the same. So that's
what רב זביד Rav Zvid says. רב זביד Rav Zvid says in
the name of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, they're both treated as mandatory
court orders and therefore if he says פרעתי, parati, we assume he'll
pay and if he says פרעתי נאמן. parati ne'eman. And because he's
believed, בא מלווה לכתוב אין כותבין ונותנין לו. ba malveh lichtov ein
kotvin venotnin lo. If the מלווה malveh wants to come later and
get a writ, we don't give it because maybe the guy already
paid. Okay, again, I presume the מלווה malveh can get a writ
right away, but he cannot get a writ later. And once you
have that court order, you're going to be believed to say you
paid. אלא אי איכא לפלוגי הכי הוא דאיכא לפלוגי. Ela i ika
lepalugi hachi hu de'ika lepalugi. If there's a distinction between the cases,
it's not between צא תן לו tzei ten lo and חייב אתה
ליתן לו, chayav ata liten lo, but the following case, because remember
we're leading up to a case of הוחזק כפרן. huchzak kafran. אמר
לו צא תן לו, Amar lo tzei ten lo, they say to
David go pay it, ואמר פרעתי, ve'amar parati, and then he comes
back and he says he paid, where he's believed, ואתו סהדי ואמרי
דלא פרע, ve'atu sahadei ve'amrei dela para, but there are witnesses to
say that he did not pay. Now Rashi has a very bizarre
read of what does that mean, how do you testify the absence
of something? So Rashi has a strange read that says like, I'm
not even going to go to Rashi, it's just going to confuse
us. I'm just going to sort of deal with what the other
ראשונים Rishonim say, which is that David says, yes, I paid him,
it was Monday at 1:00 PM, we were in front of the
ATM, I handed him the money, here I paid him. And then
witnesses say, what the heck are you talking about? You were with
us apple picking on that day. Okay, so you're known to have
lied about that in a case that otherwise you would have been
believed. הוחזק כפרן לאותו ממון. Huchzak kafran le'oto mamon. And the key
words here are לאותו ממון. le'oto mamon. Regarding this claim, you are
no longer believed. Like what Rava said before is just because you
lied about one claim does not mean you cannot be a legitimate
litigant in other claims. Okay, but in this case, you can no
longer have that believability that you had. Any claim you make now
is just automatically suspect. Okay, about in this case itself. And therefore
now you come back and you say, oh, okay, fine, I was
lying before, but now, you know, yesterday, a week ago I was
lying, but yesterday I paid you. Okay, in that case, sorry buddy,
you're no longer believed. חייב אתה, Chayav ata, okay, now that's in
that case. Okay, that's if they said צא תן לו. tzei ten
lo. Now if they said חייב אתה ליתן לו chayav ata liten
lo ואמר פרעתי, ve'amar parati, if they just said to David you're
obligated without this mandate of צא תן, tzei ten, and then he
says he paid, ואתו סהדי ואמרי דלא פרע, ve'atu sahadei ve'amrei dela
para, and witnesses testify you're lying, וחזר ואמר פרעתי, vechazar ve'amar parati,
and then you said... Fine, I was lying then, but you know,
but now I did pay you, okay, are you still believed to
say פרעתי Parati in this case, because you clearly lied already in
this case? In this case, הוחזק כפרן לאותו ממון, Huchzak kafran l'oto
mamon, you are not, your believability is not undermined. So even though
you were lying a week ago when you said you paid, here
we're going to believe you when you say you paid. It sounds
crazy, why? מאי טעמא, Mai taama, אישתמוטי הוא דקא משתמיט
מיניה, Ishtamutei hu d'ka mishtamit minei, because when you said a week
ago you paid, you were only just trying to to like avoid
having to pay right away. You weren't really not going to pay.
סבר אכתי לא פסקו רבנן לדיני, Savar achti lo pasuku rabanan l'dinei,
because you figured that look, חייב אתה ליתן לו Chayav ata liten
lo is a step prior to צא תן לו. Tze ten lo.
חייב Chayav is more in the abstract, you're obligated, but they have
yet to like issue an order to go pay. So you David
are figuring, you know, they haven't yet issued the order for me
to pay, maybe they're going to reflect and reconsider and maybe they'll
change their judgment. I'm going to postpone payment until they say צא
תן לו. Tze ten lo. Okay, because you know again, there's this
moment of final judgment at צא תן לו. Tze ten lo. So
therefore, just because you were denying it doesn't really mean you're trying
to get out of paying. The funny thing of course is is
that okay, but it still means you were lying. You weren't getting
out of paying, but you were still lying. So maybe now when
you say that you've paid, you're also not planning on stealing it,
but maybe you're also just trying to get out of paying it,
you know, at least now. It's still quite strange why, you know,
but I guess the point is just because if you weren't necessarily
such a רשע, Rasha, you still fundamentally have like believability. It still
to me it still seems quite strange, yeah.
The court system is trying to take into account human nature, yeah,
and they need to try to factor these things in too. I
understand, but we need justice.
I understand, but what I don't get is if that if a
week ago David was clearly lying, even though he wasn't planning on
stealing the money, okay, he was eventually going to pay, he was
clearly lying. So now when he says that he's paid, the most
likely thing is is that it's a repeat of last week. So
he's also lying. Right? Now, we're not going to say you're a
גנב, Gannav, you might eventually pay, but like why do we basically
believe him, like you know?
No witnesses, right?
Well, the witnesses from last week. I don't know, maybe because we
figure that if eventually he's going to pay, then even if we
trust him now or whatever, he'll still pay up the money. I
don't know, it seems strange to me.
Oh, wait, the witnesses said he didn't pay?
The witnesses said from last week that he didn't pay, but now
he claims again that he paid. Okay, anyway, the basic point is
if there's some way of rationalizing why what he did wasn't real
stealing, then he still is fundamentally believed even in this case itself,
even in this case itself. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
as follows, אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן מנה לי
בידך, Amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan mane li b'yadcha,
you owe me a hundred dollars. והוא אומר אין לך בידי כלום,
v'hu omer ein lcha b'yadi klum, I don't owe you anything. והביאו
עדים שיש לו, v'heviu edim sheyesh lo, and witnesses testify that he
does owe the money. וחזר ואמר פרעתי, v'chozar v'amar parati, fine, then
in the end he said I paid it up. הוחזק כפרן לאותו
ממון, Huchzak kafran l'oto mamon, in that case where he fundamentally denied
the whole claim even though for example it doesn't פוסל posel him
לעדות l'eidus for you know like because again you may be trying
to buy time, other types of things. Here where you fundamentally denied
the whole claim, you're considered הוחזק כפרן huchzak kafran for that money
and your claim of פרעתי parati is no longer believed. כי הא
דשבטאי בריה דרב מרינוס, Ki ha d'Shabtai breih d'Rav Marinus, like the
case of Shabtai the son of Rav Marinus, כתב לה לכלתה איצטליתא
דמילתא בכתובתה. kasav lah l'chaltaya itzlita d'milta b'ksubasa.
Okay,
so he, you know, wrote for his, you know, for his,
what do you call it, for his like daughter-in-law what, his bride?
I think it might be though his daughter-in-law. Bride?
I
think I think it might be his daughter-in-law. His daughter-in-law. וקבלה עליה,
v'kibla alei, because and he, and then he accepted responsibility, meaning it
seems that basically the son, you know, in the in the son's
כתובה ksuba he promised this particular like nice whatever it is like
silk garment or whatever, and he took responsibility if his son didn't
pay that he would pay it up. Was it in the son's
כתובה? ksuba? Yeah. אירכס כתובתה, Irkas ksubasa, the כתובה ksuba was lost.
אמר לה לא היו דברים מעולם. Amar lah lo hayu devarim me'olam.
And then he said, no, no, no, it never happened. Okay, because
the evidence of it in the כתובה ksuba that he had taken
that obligation was lost, so he denied that it ever happened. אתו
סהדי ואמרי אין כתב לה. Atu sahadei v'amrei in kasav lah. Yes,
he did write that obligation. לסוף אמר להו פרעתי. L'sof amar lehu
parati. Fine, then in the end he said I paid her up.
אתו לקמיה דרבי חייא. Atu lakamei d'Rabbi Chiya. Came to Rabbi Chiya.
So it was basically a case he denied it and then he
said he paid it up. אמר רבי חייא הוחזק כפרן לאותה איצטליתא.
Amar Rabbi Chiya huchzak kafran l'ota itzlita.
For this case, his later claim of פרעתי, parati, even though פרעתי
parati normally would be believed, here it's not believed. So I guess
when you said first פרעתי parati and you were lying and then
you say פרעתי parati again, then you're just trying to buy time
or whatever, maybe that's specifically a court case where you're hoping the
the you know the בית דין beis din will reinvestigate the case.
But in the case where it's not a court case, it's a
straight debt and you straight out deny it and you're lying, you
lose your ability afterwards to say פרעתי parati in that court case.
How did they translate? They translated it as כלתה chaltaya to mean
either bride or daughter-in-law. Daughter-in-law. They daughter-in-law. Yeah, okay. All right, so
now it says like this. אמר רב אבין אמר רב אלעזר. Amar
Rav Avin Amar Rav Elazar. So those were cases of הוחזק כפרן
לאותו ממון Huchzak Kafran L'oto Mamon
where if it's clear you're lying without any justifiable reason in this
particular case, you know your claims are no longer believed. Okay, שבועת
הפסד Shvuat Hefsed
is a, and right, שבועת הפסד Shvuat Hefsed is a rabbinic, yeah,
שבועת הפסד Shvuat Hefsed is a rabbinic right, right. אמר רב אבין
אמר רב אלעזר אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rav Avin Amar Rav Elazar
Amar Rabbi Yochanan. חייב לחברו שבועה. Chayav L'chavero Shvua. Now we're going
to, now we're going to translate this whole discussion about I already
paid you, to I already gave you the שבועה Shvua I owe
you. And this is fascinating because it treats שבועה Shvua as almost
like a type of a debt. We had that once before, you
know, ולקח עליו ולא ישלם, V'lakach Alav V'lo Yeshalem, you know, that
somehow this sense of paying somebody up a שבועה. Shvua. And what
we're going to find out is that even if you're obligated in
a שבועה, Shvua, you can make the שבועה Shvua outside of בית
דין. Beit Din. Okay, so חייב לחברו שבועה. Chayav L'chavero Shvua. You
owed a שבועה. Shvua. Now this was a case where the ראשונים
Rishonim say it means that basically, I don't know, I was a
מודה במקצת. Modeh B'miktzat. We came to the case, David told me,
you know, you borrowed $100, I said yes I borrowed 50 but
not 50, I did not borrow 50. The בית דין Beit Din
said מודה במקצת Modeh B'miktzat you're חייב Chayav to make a שבועה.
Shvua. And I'll make a שבועה Shvua and then be פטור Patur
on the other 50. Okay, ונשבעתי. V'nishbati. And I say yeah, after
we left the court, David and I were standing on the corner,
we went out for a cup of Starbucks and I made the
שבועה Shvua to him over there, which is a shocker right there.
You would think if I'm חייב Chayav a שבועה Shvua because of
a court case, I have to make the שבועה Shvua in court.
But here we find out, no, I could actually make the שבועה
Shvua anywhere, and I say I made the שבועה. Shvua. Okay, והעדים
מעידים אותו שלא נשבע. V'ha'edim Me'idim Oto Shelo Nishba.
Now it sounds like fundamentally I would be believed, the same way
I'm believed to say after בית דין Beit Din said you're חייב
Chayav to pay him $100. If they say you're חייב Chayav to
give him a שבועה, Shvua, I'm believed. Okay, again what's fascinating here
is that you would think that a שבועה Shvua is part of
the adjudication of the court, that the goal of the שבועה Shvua
is to get me to confess and to admit, right? So you
would think it would be the court that would administer the שבועה.
Shvua. People are getting this? Right, if I say yes I owe
you 50 but not the other 50 and they say you have
to make a שבועה, Shvua, presumably that's trying to prove whether I
do owe you the 50 or not. This is, and it would
have to be, you would think it would have to be done
by the court. This is being treated like the same way בית
דין Beit Din would פסק Pasken I have to pay David $100,
they're פסק'ing Pasken-ing I have to pay David a שבועה. Shvua. Okay,
if I'm not going to give him the $50 he claims, then
what he's entitled to is satisfaction, he's entitled to us to give
a שבועה Shvua from me.
Is it דאורייתא שבועה? D'oraita Shvua? Now, yes, it's a דאורייתא שבועה.
D'oraita Shvua. In Starbucks you have a ספר תורה Sefer Torah in
the Starbucks?
Okay, so there's a question like what are the specific things that
you need for דאורייתא שבועה. D'oraita Shvua. It's not so clear whether
you need all those stuff, and from this גמרא Gemara it doesn't
sound like you do. All right, but let's bracket that for a
moment. What I'm most surprised about is not whether you had the
paraphernalia, what I'm surprised about is that it's being treated as some
debt, the same way I leave court and I have to pay
you the $100, I leave court I have to pay you a
שבועה Shvua and it could be done outside of court. So I'd
be believed to say I gave you the שבועה. Shvua. But then
והעדים מעידים אותו שלא נשבע, V'ha'edim Me'idim Oto Shelo Nishba, but then
witnesses said no, no, no, we were at the Starbucks at that
time or we were there at that time, it never happened. And
then וחזר ואמר נשבעתי. V'chazar V'amar Nishbati. And then I say fine,
a week ago I was lying, I didn't do it, but then
yesterday I did give him the שבועה. Shvua. הוחזק כפרן לאותה שבועה.
Huchzak Kafran L'ota Shvua. Once it was proven that I lied about
giving him the שבועה, Shvua, I'm הוחזק כפרן. Huchzak Kafran. The same
way I could be הוחזק כפרן Huchzak Kafran when I was proven
that I was lying about the money, so now I can no
longer claim that I gave you the שבועה Shvua unless I bring
witnesses that I did. Okay, אמרוה קמיה דרבי אבהו. Amruha Kamei D'Rabbi
Abbahu. They said this to Rabbi Abbahu. אמר להו, Amar Lehu, מסתברא
מילתא דרב אבין, Mistavera Milta D'Rav Avin, you know, that position of
Rav Avin makes sense, שחייבו שבועה בבית דין, Shechiyvuh Shvua B'Beit Din,
that בית דין Beit Din obligated me to give you a שבועה.
Shvua. Because remember, the same way before, my believability and my question
about whether I'm buying him off was a function of whether they
said צא תן לו Tzei Ten Lo or חייב אתה ליתן לו,
Chayav Ata Liten Lo, you remember that before? So here too, there's
a parallel. If בית דין Beit Din tells me to make a
שבועה, Shvua, then if I'm, if I'm lying about the שבועה, Shvua,
clearly I'm trying to get out of it and I'm not believed
anymore. אבל חייב עצמו שבועה, Aval Chiyav Atzmo Shvua, but let's say
what happened was, was בית דין Beit Din didn't tell me a
שבועה. Shvua. We were having a whole fight and I said to
David, well, it'll make you happy if I make you a שבועה
Shvua on it? Like I'm not obligated, but it'll make you, he
said, yeah, then I'll be happy if you make a שבועה, Shvua,
fine, I'll make you a שבועה. Shvua. So I obligated myself to
make the שבועה. Shvua. Okay, and then I said I did make
it, and then it was proven I was lying. Am I הוחזק
כפרן Huchzak Kafran in that case? So in that case נאמן Ne'eman
or I'm not הוחזק כפרן. Huchzak Kafran. Why? אשתמוטי קא משתמיט ליה,
Ishtamutei Ka Mishtamit Lei, because you know, if it was a שבועה
Shvua that בית דין Beit Din didn't mandate me, it was a
שבועה Shvua that I obligated myself, then I similar like the גמרא
Gemara before about אשתמוטי קא משתמיט, Ishtamutei Ka Mishtamit, then I figure
like yeah, I'll say I made the שבועה Shvua even when I
didn't, like I'm not really obligated anyway. Okay, so you got the
idea. If a guy is proven to be lying about a particular
claim, like a thing about whether he paid the money or made
the שבועה, Shvua, he's no longer believed. But if we can understand
that when he said, when he was lying, he was really just,
he didn't really mean to get out of his obligation, he was
really just pushing the guy off, then he's not הוחזק כפרן Huchzak
Kafran and he's still is believed. So in one case when it's
money, חייב אתה ליתן לו, Chayav Ata Liten Lo, he figures he's
pushing him off until בית דין Beit Din can finally
reinvestigate. but he didn't treat the שבועה shvua so seriously, but it
doesn't mean that he was really getting out of it, and therefore
he's allowed to, he's still not he's still believed afterwards.
I totally get that, there's no recourse he has, he can't say
come on, give me another week, because because the guy is just
pressing him, right, you're supposed to pay me now! Right! I'm gonna
take you to court!
I'm
gonna drag you to court! He has no recourse and he has
every intent, okay, next week... I totally get it.
Okay, good. Let's move to the next case. ואמר... Va'amar... wait, you
know what, I'm gonna have to put a more moratorium on comments
because we have 15 minutes. ואמר וניחזי דמר, Va'amar v'nihzi d'mar, אהדרו
קמיה דרבי אבין, Ahadru kamei d'Rabbi Avin,
they returned this to Rabbi Avin, אמר להו אנא נמי בי דינא
נמי, Amar lehu ana nami bei dina nami, you know what, ברוך
שכיוונת. Baruch shekivanta. That was exactly my intent. When I said he's
הוחזק כפרן huchzak kaphran by by having lied about making a שבועה,
shvua, that was a שבועה shvua that was obligated in בית דין,
beis din, but not one that he imposed upon himself. איתמר נמי,
Itmar nami, is also taught, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב ואיתימא אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav v'isayma Amar Rabbi Yochanan, היה
חייב לחברו שבועה בבית דין, Haya chayav l'chavero shvua b'beis din, בית
דין beis din obligated you to make a שבועה, shvua, ואמר נשבעתי,
v'amar nishbati, and then you claimed you did, ועדים מעידים אותו שלא
נשבע, v'eidim me'idim oso shelo nishba, and witnesses say you didn't, הוחזק
כפרן לאותה שבועה, huchzak kaphran l'osa shvua, from that point on, you
are no longer believed to say you made the שבועה. shvua. אמר
רבי אסי אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Assi Amar Rabbi Yochanan. Okay,
enough with the הוחזק כפרן. huchzak kaphran. Back to finding documents. המוצא
שטר חוב בשוק, Hamotzei shtar chov bashuk, וכתוב בו הנפק, v'chasuv bo
hanpek, you found this document, it had the validation of the signatures,
okay, so basically the only question is whether we're concerned for פרוע.
parua. It definitely the money was lent, are we concerned for פרוע?
parua? So he says if וכתוב בו זמנו בו ביום, v'chasuv bo
zmano bo bayom, if the document was dated today, יחזיר לבעלים, yachazir
l'ba'alin,
then you can give it back to the owner. Why? אי משום
כתב ללוות ולא לווה, Ei mishum katav lilvos v'lo lava, if it's
because the money was never borrowed, וכתוב בו הנפק, v'chasuv bo hanpek,
no, it's been validated, which shows the money was borrowed. אי משום
פירעון, Ei mishum piraon, if it's because you're afraid that maybe the
לווה loveh already paid off, פירעא בת יומא לא חיישינן, pira bas
yoma lo chayshinan, we are not concerned that somebody borrowed money and
paid it back in the same day. Okay, so since it clearly
is today's document, we clearly it came from the מלווה. malveh. So
אמר ליה רבי זירא לרבי אסי, Amar lei Rabbi Zeira l'Rabbi Assi,
מי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? Mi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi? Does Rabbi
Yochanan really say we're not concerned for payment today, on the same
day? והא את הוא דאמרת משמיה דרבי יוחנן, V'ha at hu d'amart
mishmei d'Rabbi Yochanan, you say in the name of Rabbi Yochanan, שטר
שלווה בו ופרעו, shtar shelava bo u'pra'o, basically, you know,
David there used a שטר shtar to borrow a hundred dollars and
then he paid it up, okay, so then I gave him back
the שטר. shtar. Okay, now David wants to borrow a hundred dollars
from me again. He says, look, I prove to you that I
can pay back your things, but you know what, I need the
money again. So can I borrow another hundred dollars again? And I
say, okay, fine. And David said, hey wait, I got a great
deal, we don't even have to write up another document, I already
has a document on me that says that I borrowed a hundred
dollars from you, let's just reuse that document. You got the idea?
Yes? Okay, so in that case, אינו חוזר ולווה בו, eino chozer
v'loveh bo, he cannot use it again. Why can't he use it
again? שכבר נמחל שיעבודו, Shekvar nimchal shibudo,
because the liens that that document gave were based on the previous
loan, and those liens were were forgiven, were erased after he paid
it up. To create new liens for the new loan, you need
to write a new document. Okay, so it's like you know, it's
like you can't like you know, after you've used a match, you
can't use it again. Okay, so after you've used it, whatever liens
were created by it have been no longer valid and he can't
use it again. Now, he says, אימא, eima, now when do we
want to reuse this document? אילימא למחר וליום אחרינא, eilima l'machar u'leyom
achara,
if it's for tomorrow and the day after, meaning he borrowed me
he borrowed from me a hundred dollars in January and now it's
February, he paid it back and he wants to reuse the document
from January. How could he reuse a document that's dated January? מאי
אירייא שכבר נמחל שיעבודו, Mai irya shekvar nimchal shibudo, who has to
say that the liens have been already used up? תיפוק ליה דהוה
ליה מוקדם. Teipok lei dehavei lei mukdam. It's a שטר shtar that's
predated, right? ותנן שטרות המוקדמים פסולים, V'senan shtaros hamukdamim pesulin,
predated shtaros are not good. אלא לאו, Ela lav, the only possibility
that you could reuse a document that isn't מוקדם mukdam is that
you paid it up on that day and you want to use
it again today. Okay? אלא לאו ביומיה. Ela lav b'yomei.
So the only scenario that we have to say that you're not
allowed to reuse a שטר חוב shtar chov is David borrowed money
from me today, we wrote it on today, what's today's date? October
something... 14th... October 14th. Two hours later he pays up and now
he wants to use it again. He says, it's still dated today,
let's use it again! Okay, and so no, no, no, that you
can't do because the liens have already been used up. אלמא, Alma,
you see, פרעי אינשי ביומיה, parei inshi b'yomei, people will pay up
a debt on the same day. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said
back to him, מי קאמינא דלא פרע? Mi kamina d'la para? Did
I ever say it never happens? I'm not saying it never happens
that you pay up a debt on the same day. לא שכיח
אינשי למיפרע ביומיה קאמינא. Lo shechiach inshi l'mifrei b'yomei kamina. I said
it's not common. It's very rare. So therefore, in terms of returning
the שטר חוב, shtar chov, you don't have to be concerned about
it. You want to give a פסק psak that in the one
case in a million when it happens you're not allowed to reuse
it? גוזמא היא, Guzma hei, it does happen one case in a
million. But I'm also entitled to give a פסק psak that you
can or whatever the same Rabbi Yochanan came to the פסק psak
that you can return it if it's on the same day. Because
it's only one in a million that it would have already been
paid up. Okay, that's one read. רב כהנא *Rav Kahana*, רב כהנא
*Rav Kahana* says no, that ruling that you return it on the
same date is כשחייב מודה *kshe'chayav modeh*, when the person admits that
he has not paid up the debt. Then you can return it.
So then the גמרא *Gemara* says אי ei... הכי מאי למימרא *ee
hachi mai l'memra*, if so then it's obvious, the money was borrowed,
the person admits, obvious. And you could also ask why is it
limited to the same day? You know, as long as the person
is admitting, giving it back. גמרא *Gemara* says no, here's why it's
not obvious and here's why it has to be the same day.
No, the לוה *loveh*, the לוה *loveh* is admitting that he hasn't
paid up. He's admitting. So then why, A, it's obvious, and B,
why limit it to the same day? No, מהו דתימא *mahu de'teima*,
I might have thought המפרע פרעי *hamifra par'ei*, the לוה *loveh* really
has paid. והאי דקאמר לא פרעתי *v'ha dikamar lo parati*, why is
he saying that he didn't pay? משום דקבעי מהדר למיזפיה בזימנא אחריתי
*mishum dikaba'i mahadar l'mizpei b'zimna achreeti*, like we've been discussing. David says
he's paid up. Now he really... but he hasn't paid up, so
says give it to Dov, I haven't paid up. But really he
has, but what he's figuring is I'll give it to, you'll give
it to Dov and then I'll get Dov to lend me the
hundred dollars for the שטר shtar *shtar*, and I'll get him to
lend me money again. Now, so therefore, oops, so why not just
say you did pay up and then we'll write a new שטר
shtar *shtar*? No, ופשיטי דספרא חייש *v'pshitei d'safra chayeish*, cause you figure
look, if I, David says, if I say I've paid up and
I say he hasn't paid, so בית דין Beis Din... *beis din*
is just going to hold on to the שטר shtar, *shtar*. And
then if I want to borrow money again I'm going to have
to pay a סופר sofer *sofer* again. How can I get the
שטר shtar *shtar* back? The way I can get the שטר shtar.
*shtar* back is I'll say that I haven't paid up, so they'll
give the שטר shtar *shtar* to Dov, so that way we'll get
the שטר shtar, *shtar* back and we won't have to pay a
סופר *sofer* again. Okay, and then I'll be able to borrow money
again with the שטר *shtar*. קא משמע לן *kamashma lan*, so we're
not in a normal case, maybe we'd be concerned about this. But
anyway, no. So anyway, so I'm sorry. So therefore, oh, so why
aren't we concerned that that is what's going on in David's mind?
Why do we return it to me? קא משמע לן דאם כן
מלוה גופיה לא שביק *kamashma lan de'im kein malveh gufei lo shavik*.
No, because if that was what David was thinking, I would not
have played along. Why would I have not have played along? Meaning
I know David paid up the money. Here David is stupidly saying
he didn't pay up the money. So I'm thinking to myself, why
is David saying this? Oh, he's trying to probably get them to
give me back the שטר *shtar* because I bet he wants to
borrow money from me again. I wouldn't play along. Why would I
refuse to play along? סבר שמעי בי רבנן rabbanan ומפסדי לי *savar
shemi bei rabbanan u'mifsidi li*. The rabbis are going to find out
what's happening and they're going to make me lose out because we
just got through teaching that you can't reuse a שטר *shtar*. Okay?
So bottom line here's the story.
David says that he paid... if it was yesterday's שטר *shtar*, not
the same day, so of course we would believe David to say
that he has not paid up and give it back to me.
But if it's today's שטר *shtar*, then maybe we don't believe David.
If it's today's שטר *shtar*, why? Because maybe David wants to reuse
it because it's today's שטר *shtar*, right? And therefore, did I get
this right? Yeah, maybe we don't want David doesn't want to reuse
it because it's today's שטר *shtar*, he thinks like it can be
reused, and therefore he's saying that he didn't pay up even when
he did, in order that I can get it and we can
reuse it, and therefore we shouldn't give it back to me in
that case. We're not concerned about that because I would never play
along with that whole scheme. Okay? So now the גמרא *Gemara* says
like this... okay. מאי שנא מהא דתנן *mai shna meihad d'tenan*, one
minute. And how's it different from that which we taught? מצא שטר
חוב shtar chov. אם יש בו אחריות נכסים לא יחזיר *matza shtar
chov im yesh bo achrayut nechasim lo yachzir*. If you find a
document and it has liens, don't give it back. ואוקימנא *v'ukimna*, כשחייב
מודה *kshe'chayav modeh*. And we say that that's even when the לוה
*loveh* agrees that he still owes the money. Now why not? One
of the reasons we gave earlier was ומשום שמא כתב ללוות בניסן
ולא לוה עד תשרי *u'mishum shema katav lilvot b'Nissan v'lo lova ad
Tishrei*.
Because maybe even if he still does owe the money,
maybe it was a שטר מוקדם *shtar mukdam*, it was written in
Nissan and money wasn't borrowed until Tishrei. ואתי למיטרף לקוחות מניסן ועד
תשרי *v'atei l'mitraf lekuchot miNissan v'ad Tishrei*. Now I'm going to use
it to take out those liens that are really not legitimate, שלא
כדין *shelo k'din*. So now, remember that? We say David says he
owes money, don't return it to me because maybe, maybe the dates
were too early. That was one explanation. So according to that explanation,
why don't we say דלא אמרינן *d'lo amreinan*, why don't we say
no? Obviously there's nothing to be concerned about early dates. Why? דאם
כן מלוה גופיה לא שביק *de'im kein malveh gufei lo shavik*. If
there was really had early dates, I wouldn't have played along with
it. דאמר ליה *d'amar lei*, כתוב שטר אחרינא *ktov shtar achrina*, I
would have told David I would never have agreed in the first
place to allow David to borrow money with a document with an
earlier date. And I would have insisted that he rewrite the document
with today's date. Why? Because I don't want anything to jeopardize my
loan, right? דאמר ליה *d'amar lei*, I would have never allowed such
a document to exist. I would have said to you David, כתוב
שטר אחרינא בתשרי *ktov shtar achrina b'Tishrei*. It's Tishrei, you finally got
around to borrowing the money. We're not using this document from Nissan.
That's going to get me in trouble. Rip that up, write a
new document. I would never have allowed such a document to exist.
Why don't we say that? דדילמא שמעי בי רבנן *de'dilma shami bei
rabbanan* ומפסדי ליה. The rabbis will find out that this was an
early-dated document and I'm gonna lose my whole loan. I don't want
to jeopardize it. So why there also don't we say that the
מלווה malveh would not have allowed such a שטר to
exist? אמרי לא, Amri lo, התם hasam משום דאיכא רווחא. mishum d'ika
rivcha. No, you know, there's always this cost-benefit analysis. Yes, I'm jeopardizing
it, but I stand to gain if it's got early dates. What's
the gain I get if it's early dates? What's the gain? דקטרף
לקוחות מניסן ועד תשרי, d'katraf lakochot mi'Nisan v'ad Tishrei, it gives me
earlier liens. So in that case, even though I'm jeopardizing it because
the document might be thrown out, I'm also getting a gain, I'm
getting early liens. So מינח ניחא ליה mei'nach nicha lei ולא אמר
ליה ולא מידי. v'lo amar lei v'lo midi. I will allow David
to use an earlier document, a document that was dated from ניסן.
Nisan. Okay?
And take the risk that the בית דין...
Beis Din I'll take the risk. So therefore, are we sometimes concerned
that the מלווה malveh has gone along with a שטר that's no
good? Yes, we are sometimes concerned and that's why in that case
you don't return it. But here, that's why we said here was
today's document, today's date. So if it's today's date, I don't gain
anything by playing along with David's scheme because it doesn't give me
earlier liens. So I would say David, you want to borrow money
again? Write me a new document. I'm not going along with your
little scheme to save you five bucks for the סופר cost. Why
should I do that? It doesn't do me any good and the
document is invalid and the rabbis will find out about it. Okay?
It's really illegal, right? Right. הכא כיון דליכא רווחא, Hacha keivan d'leika
rivcha,
here
there's no benefit, דסוף סוף שטר האידנא כתיב, d'sof sof shtar ha'idna
ketiv, it's today's document, מאי איכא דקטרף לקוחות בשטר שנמחל שיעבודו, mai
ika d'katraf lakochot b'shtar she'nimchal shibudo, מאי איכא? mai ika? So what's
the, so what's going to happen with this document? דקטרף לקוחות בשטר
שנמחל
שיעבודו. D'katraf lakochot b'shtar she'nimchal shibudo. I'm gonna use this to use
for liens on something that the liens are no longer valid. Well,
that's using it illegally but to no benefit to me because just
write a new document. So לא שבק, lo shavak, I won't play
along with your scheme. So in that case, if it's today's שטר,
we say you can give it back to me. There's no reason
I would play along with your scheme. If it's a שטר from
earlier, we say don't give it back to me because maybe it's
actually a pre-dated שטר.
Okay. Now, let's keep on going. I know we only have a
few minutes but let's at least turn the דף. daf. אמר רבי
חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabi Chiya bar Abba amar
Rabi Yochanan, הטוען אחר מעשה בית דין, ha'toein achar maaseh Beis Din,
now you see why I thought we would get through today's דף,
daf, okay, לא אמר כלום. lo amar klum. If somebody says, we're
still going to, maybe if you give me five minutes over we
can actually get it done because it goes very quickly, even though
there's these big תוספות. Tosafot. If somebody basically says, a מעשה בית
דין maaseh Beis Din is a גט get that exists without a
document that בית דין beis din imposes on somebody. What is a
pre-existing debt that doesn't even require a document? א כתובה A kesubah
is a classic example. You marry a woman, okay, you're חייב chayav
a hundred or two hundred זוז. zuz. Now, there's additional amounts you
can obligate yourself, תוספת, tosefet, you know, which is the תוספת. tosefa.
But even without any written כתובה, kesubah, you're obligated in the base
amount. Also, a guy dies and his estate has to support his
wife and his daughters or whatever, you know, that is a type
of a debt that exists
even without a document being written, even without the כתובה, kesubah, those
debts exist. So if you have an obligation that is so strong
that you don't even need the document, it's just a standard obligation.
So okay, so the woman comes to her husband and says, you
know, you divorced me, pay me my כתובה, kesubah, and he says,
I paid you, okay, אינו נאמן לא אמר כלום. eino ne'eman lo
amar klum. If he claims he's paid up a מעשה בית דין,
maaseh Beis Din, he's not believed. So what do you have to
do? You're the husband. You are told you are not going to
be believed when you said you paid off that כתובה kesubah just
on the force of your words. So what are you going to
have to do if you want to pay it up and be
believed? Witnesses.
You either get witnesses or what else can you get from the
woman?
A note, a receipt, or maybe the כתובה kesubah itself. Okay and
then you would tear up the כתובה kesubah itself. Okay, but let's
take a, okay, but you're not believed based on your words that
you paid it, that you paid it. Okay. לא אמר כלום. Lo
amar klum. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? כל מעשה בית
דין כמאן דנקיט שטר בידיה דמי. Kol maaseh Beis Din k'man d'nakit
shtar b'yadei dami. If it's a מעשה בית דין maaseh Beis Din
that's so powerful, it's like she's holding onto a שטר and you
need real proof that you paid it. אמר ליה רבי חייא בר
אבא לרבי יוחנן, Amar lei Rabi Chiya bar Abba l'Rabi Yochanan, ולאו
משנתינו היא
זו?
v'lav mishnateinu
hi
zo? I don't, okay, that's a nice point but it's a מפורש
משנה. meforash Mishnah. What's the מפורש משנה? meforash Mishnah? כתובות. Kesubos. הוציאה
גט ואין עמה כתובה, Hotziah get v'ein imah kesubah,
if she took out a גט get without any accompanying כתובה, kesubah,
גובה כתובתה. govah kesubatah.
She can still collect her כתובה. kesubah. So therefore she doesn't have
a כתובה. kesubah. If she had a כתובה kesubah it would be
like a שטר חוב. shtar chov, But she doesn't have a כתובה,
kesubah, there's no שטר, it's only the power of מעשה בית דין
maaseh Beis Din and presumably it's she collects means he's not believed
to say that he paid. Okay, now of course there's a little
difference here. She has a גט. get. Maybe the גט get functions
as a כתובה kesubah or something. She still has some documentation. Okay,
so we'll see in a minute if this really proves the extent
of רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan's claim. But anyway, let's see what רבי
יוחנן Rabi Yochanan said back. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back
to
him, אי... Had I not removed the pottery shard, לא משכחת מרגניתא
תותה, lo meshkachas magenisa tusa, you wouldn't have found the pearl hiding
beneath it. Now that I've given you insight to what's going on,
now you understand this משנה, mishnah, but you wouldn't have necessarily been
able to have figured it out, you know, on your own just
from the משנה, mishnah, which also means that there's other possible explanations
for the משנה, mishnah, which is actually what אביי Abaye is going
to push
on. So אביי Abaye said, מאי מרגניתא, mai marganisa, what type of
a pearl is this? Okay, who says that this is what the
משנה mishnah means? אימא במקום שאין כותבין כתובה עסקינן, eima b'makom she'ein
kosing kesuvah askinan, דגט היינו כתובתה, de'get hainu kesuvashah, in a place
where there's no כתובה kesuvah written, the גט get functions as... right,
if all you have is מעשה בית דין, ma'aseh beis din, then
we're going to say we're going to treat the גט get as
the כתובה, kesuvah, and if she produces a גט, get, then you're
not believed to say you paid. But let's say she can't find
the גט, get, or let's say the גט get has been torn
up or whatever it is, and she has no גט get and
no כתובה, kesuvah, you wouldn't be believed. But maybe אביי Abaye is
saying, maybe you always need in order that the claim 'I paid'
won't be believed, the woman always needs some form of documentation, either
a physical כתובה kesuvah or a physical גט. get. So in a
place where they don't write a כתובה, kesuvah, the גט get functions
as the כתובה. kesuvah. Right, exactly. אבל במקום שכותבין כתובה, aval b'makom
shekosing kesuvah, but in a place where you do write the כתובה,
kesuvah, then without... then the גט get is not the substitute. אי
נקטה כתובה גביא ואי לא לא גביא. ei nakta kesuvah gavya ve'ei
lo lo gavya. If she has a כתובה kesuvah she collects, if
not, no. Meaning, not that she doesn't collect, but that he's believed
to say 'I paid up'. So where do you see that it
doesn't work like any other שטר חוב, which is without documentation the
guy's believed to say he paid up? Okay, so אביי Abaye says,
'I don't see it at all from this משנה.' mishnah. הדר אמר
אביי, hadar amar Abaye, but then אביי Abaye said, 'You know what?
בר מן דין דאמי, bar min dein de'ami, what I just said,
forget it, this doesn't make sense. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was really
right. דאי סלקא דעתך במקום שאין כותבין כתובה עסקינן אבל במקום שכותבין
כתובה אי נקטה כתובה גביא ואי לא לא גביא, dei salka dachasach
b'makom she'ein kosing kesuvah askinan aval b'makom shekosing kesuvah ei nakta kesuvah
gavya ve'ei lo lo gavya, if the case where she can collect
without the כתובה, kesuvah, the place where כתובה kesuvah normally isn't written,
but when כתובה kesuvah is written then she only collects with the
physical כתובה, kesuvah, if that's true, אלמנה מן האירוסין במה גביא? almanah
min ha'eirusin b'mai gavya? Let's say a woman is a widow from
אירוסין. eirusin. Now why is this significant? Because the כתובה kesuvah wasn't
written until the נישואין. nisuin. And if she's an אלמנה, almanah, she
doesn't have
a גט. get. So she has neither a גט get nor a
כתובה. kesuvah. Got it? Okay, she's an אלמנה almanah so there's no
she's an אירוסין, eirusin, no כתובה. kesuvah. The obligation of the כתובה
kesuvah began by אירוסין, eirusin, but the document wasn't written until נישואין.
nisuin. So there's no כתובה kesuvah and she's an אלמנה almanah so
there's no גט. get.
And it's a מקום שכותבין כתובה. makom shekosing kesuvah. In מקום שכותבין.
makom shekosing. So במה גביא? b'mai gavya? If you were to say
that the rule is, in this place, you always need a physical
document, okay, and basically what אביי Abaye is really saying because before
we actually said the גט get would be a substitute document, if
we always need a document and certainly
in במקום שכותבין כתובה b'makom shekosing kesuvah we certainly always need a
document, so in this case, במה גביא? b'mai gavya? What should she
collect based on? בסהדי דמית בעל, b'sahadei d'mis ba'al, witnesses that the
husband died? ליתון ולימא פרעתי. leison u'leima parati. So the orphans will
say, whatever, that we paid it up. וכי תימא הכי נמי. ve'chi
teima hachi nami. Okay, maybe they can say that. אם כן מה
הועילו חכמים בתקנתם? im kein mah ho'ilu chachamim b'takanasam? So why did
the חכמים chachamim establish that an אלמנה מן האירוסין almanah min ha'eirusin
gets a כתובה? kesuvah? Everybody will always just say, 'Who knows, maybe
our father paid' and end of story. So you see that since
this woman...
she's
entitled for כתובה kesuvah from the אירוסין. eirusin.
Where do the children come from?
Ah, from another marriage, I guess. That's a good point. From another
marriage. Whoever the heirs are, whoever the heirs of the estate are,
it doesn't matter. There are some heirs of the estate, I don't
care who they are. Okay, אם כן מה הועילו חכמים בתקנתם. im
kein mah ho'ilu chachamim b'takanasam. So anyway, so you see that since
she can collect without documentation, that it really is true that even
without any documentation, and therefore we're going to use that to say
that even when she has the כתובה kesuvah and says the כתובה
kesuvah was lost or whatever she does, she's always believed without documentation
and he can't say 'paid up'. Which, by the way, means that
if he gets the כתובה kesuvah back from her, it's not he
should not tear it up, or if he's going to tear it
up, he should tear it up but hold on to it, because
if he tears it up and burns it and throws it out,
she'll just say 'you never paid me'. Right, because that's part of
the חידוש chiddush of this, that she doesn't produce a כתובה, kesuvah,
even if we knew a כתובה kesuvah existed, they'll say 'Where's the
כתובה?' kesuvah? 'I don't know, I lost it.' Okay, she can just
claim she lost it or whatever, and she nevertheless will be believed.
Now we're also so, a, if you get the כתובה kesuvah from
her, hold on to it for proof that you paid. Better, get
a receipt. Because there's another possibility: maybe it hasn't been paid, she
says 'I lost it', she's hiding it, he pays her, and then
she comes back to another בית דין a year later and she
produces the כתובה kesuvah and she collects a second time. So there's
all these possible abuses. I mean, on one hand, we're protecting the
woman's interests, but there's all these possible abuses. The only way the
guy can really protect himself is... by either getting the כתובה kesuba
and holding onto it or by getting a receipt, okay? So that's
why תוספות Tosafos says that the basic position here is כותבין שובר,
kotvin shovar, that you know there's a whole debate whether you demand
you can demand some like you assume that you have the right
to and can demand a receipt or whatever or so anyway that's
the presumption here. We're going to give the woman all these protections
that even a place where there's a כתובה, kesuba, he's not believed
to say he paid even if she doesn't produce her כתובה kesuba
and his obligation is to make sure he gets a receipt and
holds on to it. So let's do one more sentence here, I
know we're a little over but anyway. אמרי מר קשישא בריה דרב
חסדא לרב אשי, Amrei Mar Kashisha berei d'Rav Chisda l'Rav Ashi, ואלמנה
מן האירוסין דאית לה כתובה מנלן? v'almanah min ha'eirusin d'is lah kesuba
minalan?
One minute buddy, your whole proof was that you assume that an
אלמנה almanah from the אירוסין eirusin has a כתובה. kesuba. How do
you know that the כתובה kesuba obligations begin in אירוסין? eirusin? Because
most of the כתובה kesuba obligations begin in the נישואין. nissuim. All
of the reciprocal obligations of support begin in the נישואין, nissuim, the
תוספת, tosefes, the additional amount that the husband offers, begins at the
נישואין. nissuim. So how do you know that the base amount already
begins at the אירוסין? eirusin? אילימא מהא דתנן, Ilima meha detnan, נישאת
או נתגרשה בין מן האירוסין ובין מן הנישואין גובה את הכל. nis'es
o nisgareshah bein min ha'eirusin uvein min hanissuim govah es hakol.
It says if a woman is divorced or widowed, whether from אירוסין,
eirusin, whether from נישואין, nissuim, she collects the full amount. So look,
it's clear, even from אירוסין eirusin she collects it. No, דילמא היכא
דכתב לה. dilma heicha dechasav lah.
Maybe that's a case where he wrote a כתובה kesuba from אירוסין.
eirusin. If a כתובה kesuba was written from אירוסין, eirusin, she gets
it. But how do you know she's entitled to it without it
being written? וכי תימא מאי לממרא? v'chi teima mai l'memra? One minute,
if he wrote it from אירוסין, eirusin, so of course she collects.
What's the חידוש chiddush that he wrote a document she collects? No,
לאפוקי מדרבי אלעזר בן עזריה, l'afukei mi'd'Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah, דאמר שלא
כתב לה אלא על מנת לכונסה, d'amar shelo chasav lah ela al
mnas l'chonsah, איצטריכא ליה. itztricha lei.
Because רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah says, let's say
from אירוסין eirusin I wrote to my bride here, I'm going to
give you the base amount of 200 plus an extra 10,000 as
a תוספת tosefes because I love you, okay? And then I divorce
her from the אירוסין. eirusin. So the question is does she get
the extra 10,000? רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah says
even though I wrote it at the time of אירוסין, eirusin, the
purpose of the תוספת tosefes was looking forward towards the eventual חופה.
chuppah. So she's not entitled to the תוספת tosefes until the חופה.
chuppah. You got it? I wrote it in the אירוסין eirusin but
she's not entitled until the חופה, chuppah, even though it's written. So
therefore the רבנן are saying no, she gets if you wrote it,
she gets everything you wrote, even from the אירוסין. eirusin. Okay, דיקא
נמי דקתני גובה את הכל,
deika nami d'kasani
govah es hakol, collects it all. אי אמרת בשלמא דכתב לה, ei
amart bishlama dechasav lah, the point was that he wrote it and
there's more than just the base amount, there's a תוספת, tosefes, היינו
דקתני גובה את הכל. hainu d'kasani govah es hakol. So the חידוש
chiddush is not only does she collect the base amount, you wrote
it, she collects everything, even the תוספת. tosefes. אלא אי אמרת דלא
כתב לה, ela ei amart d'lo chasav lah, but if there's no
written document, מאי גובה את הכל? mai govah es hakol? What do
you mean collects it all? It should have said somebody who's an
אלמנה almanah or a גרושה gerushah from אירוסין, eirusin, מנה ומאתים דאית
לה, maneh umasayim d'is lah, she gets the base amount. So this
ברייתא braisa that says that a woman gets the כתובה kesuba from
אירוסין eirusin might only be talking about when there was a written
כתובה. kesuba. So what we have yet to do is prove אביי
Abaye is like you know the assumption we had that a woman
from אירוסין eirusin without a written כתובה kesuba is still entitled to
100 or 200. So we will pick up with this on שבת,
Shabbos, God willing on שבת Shabbos we'll fully catch up. Thank you.